Will this past week's critical economic
updates be enough to keep central
bankers from being, well, central
bankers, chasing oil prices with the
rate hikes? We got numbers from all over
the place, starting with the Eurozone,
barely positive. Canada, well, that one
bounced back. That makes two up and two
down over the last year. Mexico, and
keep in mind, Mexico is very often a
proxy for the United States and US
demand, Mexico put in a big-time
contraction in the first quarter. And
then the US itself, missed expectations
with consumer weakness all over that
report. And keep in mind, all of this is
before the full energy shock weighs in.
And this is very likely why central
bankers last week had to pause before
they end up doing what they all really
want to do. Now, one thing is for sure,
every last one of these critical reports
show the rate cuts over the past couple
years did not make a difference. That's
why rate cutting is like Pringles. We've
been telling you the whole time they
don't work. So, they have to keep going
on back into the Pringles can, because
once you start, you can't stop. And
that's true, even in a situation like
this where initially it might seem like
the Pringles are done, the rate cutting
is over. After all, I fully expect the
Europeans, probably the Bank of England,
too, they're going to raise their policy
rates and maybe as soon as next month.
That depends on how they react to the
data we're going to go over here today.
However, given what that data did show,
it's just more proof that however
officials might respond in near term,
the end result is going to be the same
nonetheless. The world had already lost
a ton of momentum late last year and in
early part of this one. In other words,
what these numbers already show is a
wide-open path right back in to the
Pringles can, and that's only the start
of it. So, Steve, we got a whole bunch
of economic data this past week. At the
same time, we got, you know, five major
central banks, you know, Japan, the
Federal Reserve, Bank of Canada, Bank of
England, ECB. They all met. And I was
kind of surprised cuz I thought maybe
one or two might hike rates this week.
It sounds like they're going to hike in
the in
their next meetings, the next range of
meetings next month, but even before we
get to the rate hikes, you got to look
at where the economy is. And the economy
is, according to the GDP numbers, not in
all that great shape. And again, this is
before we get to April and the real
heavy energy shock. So, back, you know,
March is there, oil prices started to go
up, but already a weak in economy before
it.
Yeah, Jeff, and to me this wasn't really
a surprise, because, you know, you see
these energy shocks, obviously, you
know, where I think we're on roughly day
60 of this, you know, spike in prices.
We know here in the US, obviously,
consumers did get, you know, the extra
tax refund money. We know businesses are
going to at some point get some tariff
money back. Or all of that, I, you know,
I don't know the exact details of what
they're getting, but nevertheless, what
is still the overall trend around the
world is it's a deceleration. And of
course, you know, all this looks like is
we're headed right into global
stagflation. And this is a problem
because you you would expect the central
bankers to do something. Now, I agree,
you know, perhaps in Europe and in
Japan, there's there is the case for
them to hike rates, even though we know
that would be a terrible move. The
problem is they see inflation and they
get panicked about it and they think
they have to react to it and they don't
realize that consumers all over the
world, for a short period of time, they
can afford this increase in prices, but
historically, we look back and we know
exactly where things go when they can't.
And the problem is central bankers just
don't have any perspective on the
average consumer around the world, which
is again leading us to exactly what
typically happens at this stage, our
policy mistakes.
Now, this episode is sponsored by
Augusta Precious Metals. Now, most of
what we cover on the show is how the
financial system actually works, the
mechanics, the incentives, the plumbing.
But one question I get from everybody
is, okay, I understand everything now,
but what do I do with this? Now, I can't
answer that question for you,
everybody's different, but one thing
worth understanding is that a lot of
retirement accounts are built around a
pretty narrow set of asset types. Most
people never learn what else is
available to them. Physical gold held in
an IRA is one of those options. Now,
whether it makes sense for you, that's a
separate question. And the reason I'm
comfortable pointing people to Augusta
Precious Metals is that their approach
is education first, just like us at Euro
Dollar University. They'll walk you
through how a gold IRA actually works,
the mechanics, the fees, the custodial
side, and let you decide if it's
relevant to your situation. If you want
to learn more, go to eurodollargold.com
or text euro to 35052,
and they'll send you a free guide. Now,
Augusta Precious Metals is a paid
sponsor, and we thank them for their
sponsorship. This is for educational
purposes only and not investment advice.
Consult a qualified financial
professional before making any
investment decisions. Yeah, the policy
mis- Well, I mean, let's talk about the
rate cuts. Those were a policy mistake,
too, right? Because what we're talking
about with these GDP numbers, and we'll
go into the details in a second here,
with all these GDP numbers in every
place around the world, what it shows is
the rate cuts didn't work. So, if the
rate cuts didn't work, why would rate
rate hikes actually work? Um and of
course, we talk about this all the time
that, you know, interest rate policies
among central banks really are kind of
irrelevant. Uh they they end up chasing
uh events in the marketplace or in the
real economy, right? The economy started
to get weak 2023 heading into 2024. Why
did it get weak? Well, we had another
oil energy shock in 2023 and early 2024.
And what happened? The global economy
started to fall off. We're still seeing
the aftermath of that here in 2026. So,
all these central banks responded to
that with the Pringles can. They started
cutting rates. And once they started
cutting rates, just like the ad said for
Pringles, once you start, you can't
stop. And so, they cut rates and they
cut rates and they cut rates, and they
thought, well, we did a great job
cutting rates. The GDP numbers say you
didn't do anything. The weakness that
was there heading into 2024 is still
there now in early 2026. So, what
happens now? Oil prices start to go
higher, and central bankers, they
respond to oil prices, and they say, now
we have to raise rates because consumer
price rates are going to go up, which we
know that they will. In fact, they
already have. So, consumer price numbers
are going to go higher. Central bankers
are likely to chase them with their
higher rates, which won't do anything
because it makes no difference. And the
reason it makes no difference, what
Steve just said, historically, you have
a weak economy that really cannot absorb
repeated hits. But it does or it absorbs
hit after hit after hit. But then, you
know, an energy shock is a different
animal. The reason an energy shock is a
different animal is because gasoline,
diesel in particular, these are price
inelastic goods, which means you can't
really do anything about it. If if oil
prices go up and energy prices go up,
you got to pay. You can't really cut
back on the amount of energy that you
use. Yeah, I mean, consumers, you can
drive a little bit less, maybe you don't
go to Walmart every day, maybe you go to
Dollar General and Walmart and run your
errands at the same time, but that
really doesn't save a whole lot. And as
far as businesses in the real economy,
you really can't cut back on fuel. So,
costs go up, you really don't have much
options, especially this is where the
weak economy really comes in.
In a healthy economy, an energy shock
shows up and maybe you think, okay, we
can absorb it, business is booming,
we're doing really well, so we'll take
the hit and get through the short run
and everything will be fine. In the
weakened state that we're seeing in all
these GDP numbers, very different story.
The costs go up and you're like, what
the hell are we going to do now? You
have to start laying off workers,
cutting back hours, cutting back
incomes. Consumers, they have to pay
more at the pump, which they're paying a
lot more at the pump, which means, as we
know, Steve, they have to cut back in
their spending, largely discretionary
spending, which means services, and it
gets to be an even bigger mess.
You know, Jeff, and I think that is the
real key point here as you look at
lower-income and middle-income
consumers, and not just here in America,
but all over the world. And what do we
continue to hear is, hey, prices are too
high. So, now, as you said, yeah, gas
prices are up, energy prices are up,
particularly as we go into the summer,
their spending has to get offset
somewhere else. And that's exactly what
starts to happen. And yet, here we are
in the middle of the shock, and what's
happening? We still look at, you know,
manufacturers, they're, hey, we got to,
you know, crank out production cuz we
have to front-run inflation. The problem
is they can't see the end. you can build
all you want, but I can't afford I
couldn't afford it 2 weeks ago, I
couldn't afford it 2 months ago, and I
certainly can't afford it now. And you
still look out even further, and what is
the expectation, at least in food
prices? Yeah, somewhere in the next 3, 6
months, where those are expected to go
up even more. So, you talk about the
repeated blows, but there are certain
people, you know, again, the the
lower-income, middle-income consumers,
they are going to have to significantly
cut their spending. This is what we're
hearing from the airlines. Hey, people
aren't wanting to fly as much. People
are looking at staycations. There just
isn't the money, and that's the
challenge. You get these huge build-up
in inventories, then you start to see
the services sector, as you said, start
to go down, which is a great leading
indicator here. And next thing you know,
you're at the point of no return.
Yeah, you're right about the
manufacturing, too, right, Steve? We got
the ISM on Friday, the ISM manufacturing
index on Friday. And while the index was
steady overall and in in new orders
picked up, the employment index actually
fell pretty sharply, which is number
one, when manufacturers saying, yes,
we're churning out a bunch of product is
companies around the world are emergency
stockpiling, you know, they're trying to
get everything built and done before
prices go up or materials really fall
into short supply. We talked about this
last week, right? Plastic is a huge one.
There's going to be a plastic shortage,
and that's going to cause a lot of
problems. So, you've got manufacturers,
their fax machines are going off the
hook here. They're just worrying,
worrying, and worrying, but they're not
hiring anybody. The reason they're not
hiring anybody, number one, they say,
this isn't going to last. And number
two, their costs are going way up. The
ISM's manufacturing price index soared
to its highest in 4 years, which tells
you their costs are going up. Maybe
they're getting away with raising their
selling prices a little bit, but they're
being squeezed at the margins. So, at
the same time, they're busy, they're
cutting back on employment, which is
exactly what we're saying here. It's
forcing economic participants to have to
choose and have to choose from a very
weak state, from a very weak start.
We've talked about this before. The idea
was that, you know, weakness in 2025 was
all about trade wars and tariffs. And
once the world normalized to tariff
uncertainty, we'd be on an upswing late
2025 heading into 2026. But all the data
shows
there was an artificial high in the
summertime as we got another rush of
activity to beat out the tariff deals
that were actually hammered out. There
was some pickup in employment, um you
know, in the US and Canada to a certain
extent around the same time artificial
high, but by the time you get to
October, November, and certainly
December, then the beginning of 2026,
everything is going in the opposite
direction. And again, that's before we
get to March and April. So, all the
numbers really say
there was no pickup last year, at least
not a sustained pickup, and we started
2026 on a downswing before we even get
to the real real real nasty energy
prices.
Yeah, Jeff. And you know, right now the
economy, you know, you look at the stock
market saying, well, you know, looks
like there's some sort of booster. Of
course, we know this is all about, you
know, the tax refund checks.
>> S&P's going to make it to 8,000, Steve?
Is that what you're saying here? I you
know, Jeff, I'm glad you brought that up
because I do think that's a possibility.
I'm not sure you know, we haven't talked
about that yet, but you know,
nevertheless, you look at these
manufacturers and what are they very
clearly telling us? As you said, they're
being squeezed. So, you have to make a
choice. And they know, as you said,
look, we're getting this flush of orders
in, but we know it's not going to last.
But what about these AI companies? You
We're seeing the same exact thing. Hey,
we've got to spend all this money on
build out, we need more CapEx, and
what's the sacrifice? We've got to cut
more employees. You look at the services
sector. What are the airlines saying?
Hey, we got to cut capacity, cut routes,
and cut planes. And well, they didn't
say that means cut employees, but
obviously we know it means cut
employees. So, as you go into the summer
season here, this is where you really
want to see the economy you're really
starting to accelerate. You want to see
businesses hiring as consumers go out
and spend. And it seems like
we're close, maybe within a month or so
of seeing kind of a cliff hit as
consumers run out of money from
their tax refund checks and have nowhere
to turn. And at this point, businesses,
mode, as you said, Jeff, and they're
going to have no choice. These These job
cuts are going to get far, far worse.
Let's talk about Europe because I think
Europe is one of the bellwethers that we
need to watch. I mean, Asia, they're
directly impacted by the disruption of
petroleum in the Middle East. So, the
demand destruction that shows up in Asia
could just be because, hey, we don't
have any fuel. Now, Europe, it's more of
a price effect as well as a energy
shortage. So, I think Europe is sort of
the leading indicator for where the rest
of the world goes. If the energy shock
is at all being contained in, say, Asia
or you know, those those areas that are
most directly affected by the Middle
Eastern shut shutdowns, um that's one
thing. But if you start to see the
weakness really spread in Europe, then
that's where you really start to start
to get concerned about the rest of the
globally synchronized world. And what
have we seen? We've seen European
sentiment that is absolutely crashed.
Consumer sentiment is down. Commercial
sentiments like the Germany's IFO,
that's down pretty sharply. The European
Commission's sentiment indicators for
especially services, that was down to a
60-month low. Retail sentiment was like
a 61-month low. S&P Global Services PMI
was a 62-month low. And yes, there's a
theme here. Uh the employment index in
Europe, down to another five-year low.
So, Europe in sentiment is already
starting to look in the way that you
would expect in an energy shock. And
then you add to that the GDP numbers,
which are looking backward, but it does
tell you it gives you a sense of why
European sentiment would just utterly
crash seemingly all at once because,
like I said, the weak state of the
economy heading into 2026. And you look
GDP. So, the the Europeans reported for
GDP in the first quarter an increase of
just 0.12%.
Um not quite zero, but close to zero.
Not only that, then the fourth quarter
European GDP was up 3/10 of a percent, a
little bit better than 3/10 of a
percent, which that seemed like the
second straight quarter of accelerating
GDP growth, which is why Christine
Lagarde kept running around everywhere
saying, "We're in a good place. We're in
a good place. We're in a good place."
Well, Eurostat just said, "Guess what?
You weren't in a good place. That 3.
that 0.33% growth rate you thought you
had, it's actually 0.18." So, already in
the fourth quarter you see a little bit
of deceleration, and that deceleration
continued in the first quarter. And then
you look at GDP in the context in any
meaningful historical context, you see
it hasn't really grown in years. So,
everybody's getting excited about three
a third of a percentage point increase
in the fourth quarter that just
disappeared. That wasn't even actual
legitimate growth to begin with. And now
it's decelerating all over again, just
as we said, just as the markets were
predicting. So, you've got an economy in
Europe that's in really bad shape, that
was decelerating to end last year, and
then along comes an energy shock, and of
course, you're going to see sentiment
absolutely plunge because you have all
the key ingredients for the historical
energy shock case. As you said last
week, Steve, you get an energy shock
ahead of each post-war reces- well, each
each recession since the 1970s. So, over
the last half century, those two things
go together. You get a weak economy, you
get an energy price spike, and next
thing you know, you've got a full-blown,
yes, this is absolutely a recession.
But Jeff, central bankers have no
choice. They've got to say everything's
okay because, as you said earlier and as
we know very much, the rate cuts don't
work, and they particularly do not work
during stagflation because you have this
continued acceleration in prices, and
you could see this going into every
recession, and then the labor market
starts to go, and that's kind of the big
red flag. You know, when I saw the PMIs
today in the manufacturing sector, I
said, "Whoa." You know, I I knew the
numbers were going to be up. I knew new
orders were going to be up.
That wasn't what I really straightened
looked for. I was looking at the
employment, and that was huge because
you look at the weekly claims data this
week, and it would give you some sense
that perhaps, you know, businesses are
out hiring again. We saw, you know,
initial claims drop. We saw continued
claims drop. Now, what we don't know is
what those jobs actually are, but these
higher-paying manufacturing jobs, wow,
this is a big shock. So, you think from
a central banker's perspective, they've
got to cheer anything because they know
if they cut rates at this point and the
labor market starts to go and inflation
stays up, there's you can make rates
negative infinity, and it won't make a
lick of a difference. And that's the
problem they're facing is, you know,
we talked about Japan before the show
is, why don't they raise rates when, of
course, their model says we've got to
raise rates, but they don't because they
know it doesn't do anything, but it's
all about central bank credibility. Now,
you and I and our audience, we know they
have virtually done, but for the stock
market and a lot of people out there,
they think, "Hey, this really matters."
But it's not going to matter at all
because as we see the energy crisis
continue,
central bankers are going to end up
cutting rates as the labor market goes,
and it won't make any difference as they
cut all the way back to zero.
Yeah, we have to keep in mind the ECB
cut its rates, its policy rate, the
deposit rate floor, which is now their
main rate, down to 2% in the middle of
last year, and it did didn't do a damn
bit of good. Didn't do absolutely
anything. You look at the output
numbers, employment, none of it changed
because they were lowering rates. In
fact, they were lowering rates because
of the economic circumstances. As like
we said, interest rates are not
stimulus. They don't fix the economy,
they're a reaction to it. And so again,
rate hikes are a reaction to consumer
prices rather than anything else. And
what we're saying is that with this
weakened economic economic circumstance
heading into the energy shock, sure,
central banks are going to hike rates in
the short run, but what's going to
happen in the intermediate term is like
the historical energy shock case,
they're going to end up chasing the
weakness because the weakness is going
to become apparent. Let's talk about
another one, Steve. Let's talk about
Mexico. Let's bring this a little bit
closer to the United States. Mexico is
often a proxy for the United States for
obvious reasons because we're right next
to each other, biggest trading partner.
US demand is good, Mexico's economy is
largely good. There's some, you know,
other factors involved. Sure, local
factors, what the Chinese are doing as
far as nearshoring, especially in the
2020s. But by and large, Mexico can be a
proxy for the US economy. And we better
hope that's not the case given the
latest economic data. For the first
quarter of this year, Mexican GDP was
down by 8/10 of a percent. Now, it was
up by 9/10 of a percent in the fourth
quarter, but it was down in the third
quarter and up in the up in the second
quarter of last year. In fact, over the
last eight quarters, Mexican GDP has
been negative in four of them, not
consecutively. So, as far as most people
are concerned, Mexico is not in a
recession because it doesn't meet the
technical definition of two straight
quarters. But what do you call a
situation where for an entire year GDP
goes up and down, up and down, which
means it goes nowhere. But it's not just
an entire year, it goes back even
further, or actually two years. We're
talking about four of the last eight. Go
back the last 10 quarters, which brings
us back to 2023. Out of those 10
quarters, GDP was negative in four of
them and barely positive in three
additional ones. So, it was only really
positive in three out of the 10. So, for
a two and a quarter or two and a
half-year period, Mexico has gone this
way. And what has Mexican central
Mexico's central bank done during that
two and a half-year period? Well,
they've been eating up Pringles left and
right. They've been cutting rates,
including the last meeting in March.
Banxico took a lot of heat because in
March, while all the other central
bankers were talking about hiking rates,
oil prices are up, the Mexican central
bankers, to their to their limited
credit, said, "You know what? We're
probably going to need to cut rates."
They were way ahead of the curve. They
said, "Look, we see the weakness
coming." And then the GDP report for the
first first quarter comes out and it
says, "Yeah, you guys are right." And so
where this brings us right back to the
same same idea here. Now, we're
US adjacent. We're talking about Mexico
here. No economic growth for two and a
half years. More and more weakness
showing up in the first quarter before
we get the energy shock. It's it's more
evidence for that historical case. Weak
economy meets energy shock, which leads
to, first of all, central bankers
overreacting on the on the price side,
and then eventually they realize they
made a huge mistake when the economy
really starts to get weak from there.
Yeah, Jeff, cuz you know, you think
about it like the average consumer. You
know, we talked about rate cuts and why
why they make no difference here because
you you you just mentioned Mexico. The
economy is going flat but what about all
of the debt? And that's the thing is you
need economic growth to pay on the debt
and to keep the economy growing. So flat
might as well be a recession even though
technically it isn't a recession. But
you think about by the time you cut
rates, you know,
how about the family saying, "Hey, you
know, we were going to do a little
weekend trip but hey, we go to the
grocery store and wow, food prices are
up, go to the gas station on the way
out, that's up. We can't afford that
trip." You cutting rates, they're not
going to go and put that trip on their
credit card say, "Hey kids, let's go
out, you know, go camping and we're
going to finance this whole thing." It's
not going to happen. But yet the central
bankers for some reason have this weird
perspective of, you know, the average
person but this is why it doesn't work.
The only choice they have is to cut
spending because they've also got their
debt on top of this. So they're looking
out at the economy, they're saying,
"Hey, people are losing their jobs like
in the manufacturing sector." Yes, the
economy's hiring but probably low wage
summer seasonal jobs. This isn't the
right path. So yes, the tax cuts are
being spent which really kind of
surprised me, Jeff. I thought they would
get saved or used to pay down debt.
Based on at least the retail sales data,
it looks like they're spending. The only
question now is for how much longer and
when that stops and it's going to stop,
these central bankers, as you said, are
going to go from one extreme to talking
rates up to being like, "Oh my god, we
have to slash them to next to nothing,
probably all the zero." And the only
thing that's going to matter in the
beginning is the stock market's going to
love that next rate cut until the
reality comes into perspective that,
"Hey, we're going right into
stagflation, rate cuts aren't working
and the only thing we're staring is over
the edge of the cliff."
Well Steve, don't you think with the tax
cuts that consumers just they didn't
have a choice? I mean, here comes a
little bit of extra money, a couple
hundred dollars. What's the average?
Like $350 per taxpayer. You know, I
think I saw the average increase in
gasoline prices that people are paying
are like a couple hundred dollars a
month. So one goes right to the other. I
think a lot of Americans said, "Look,
I've got some tax refund. Uh I'm paying
more for get I'm just going to spend it
right on gasoline and not really have to
cut back and hope in hope that the that
this whole, you know, energy shock just
goes away maybe next month or the month
after that and we won't have to continue
to do this. So
Um let's talk let's finish up here with
the US GDP report cuz there are a couple
of points that were there that I think
are worth uh especially in the context
of the discussion we're having here. You
saw services spending decelerate again.
So the fourth quarter services spending
was a little bit weak and then the first
quarter was even weaker still even
though the first quarter overall
rebounded and as we know, as everybody
knows by now, the first quarter GDP
rebounded largely because of AI data
center buildout. So I mean, we are
doubly indebted, I use that term pun
intended here. We're doubly indebted to
the AI bubble cuz not only is it is it
responsible for GDP growth or the vast
majority of it now, it's also
responsible for Steve's hat which means
getting wealthy people to continue
spending, you got to have the AI bubble
anchoring of the stock market. So if
something happens to the AI bubble,
you've seen consumers cutting back on
services so that they can spend more on
goods, not because they're buying more
goods but because the prices of goods
are going up. This is really a bad
situation and then if the AI bubble
really does start to weaken or start to
reverse, then you just kick that last
leg out from under the very weak stool
that's that's already there and you're
in real in real trouble uh which is I
think one reason why the Federal
Reserve, yeah, there were three
dissenters who thought that you know,
the Fed should not talk about rate cuts
but by and large the committee realizes
like the Canadian their Canadian
counterparts, there's more weakness on
the downside than there is really
sustained inflation on the upside.
Huge thanks to Steve as always for
stopping by and to Augusta Precious
Metals, thank them for their
sponsorship, check them out. There's a
link in the description. If you want to
know what's going on with pawn shops and
the pawn shop signal, that's the video
link below. And as always, thank you
very much for joining me. Huge thank you
as always to Euro Dollar University
members and subscribers and until next
time, take care.